Register of the Ivo D. Duchacek Papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Ivo D. Duchacek papers,
1939-1988
81063
Duchacek, Ivo D., 1913-
25 manuscript boxes, 7 phonotape cassettes (10.8 linear feet)
Hoover Institution on War, Revolution, and Peace Stanford, California 94305-6010
Radio broadcast recordings and transcripts, writings, diaries, dispatches, correspondence, and printed matter, relating to Czechoslovakia during World War II, wartime diplomacy, Soviet annexation of Ruthenia in 1945, the communist coup of 1948, and American broadcasting to Czechoslovakia.
Administrative Information
Access
Collection is open for research.
Access to audiovisual materials requires at least two weeks advance notice. Audiovisual materials include sound recordings, video recordings, and motion picture film. Hoover staff will determine whether use copies of the materials requested can be made available. Some materials may not be accessible even with advance notice. Please contact the Hoover Institution Archives Audiovisual Specialist for further information.
Acquisition Information
Acquired.
Accruals
Increments may have been received since this finding aid was prepared. Please check Stanford University's online catalog Socrates at http://library.stanford.edu/webcat to find the full extent of the collection.
Alternative Form Available
Also available on microfilm (25 reels).
Biographical Note
1913 February 27 Born, Prostejov, Czechoslovakia
1936-1939 Correspondent for Lidove noviny in Paris
1939-1945 Diplomatic officer, Government in Exile, London
1940-1944 Broadcast weekly commentaries on BBC to German-occupied Czechoslovakia
1941-1945 Chef de cabinet to the deputy minister of foreign affairs, Hubert Ripka
1945 Returned to Czechoslovakia as a liaison officer with General Patton's third army
1945-1948 Chief-editor and co-founder (with Pavel Tigrid) of Obzory Leader of the Czechoslovak People's Party, Member of the Czechoslovak Parliament, and chairman of the Foreign Affairs Committee of the National Assembly
1948 February Dismissed from the Czechoslovak People's Party, and after the Coup d'Etat emigrated to Great Britain, and later to the United States
1948-1953 Professor of political science, Yale University
1949-1954 Editor-in-chief, Czechoslovak Service, Voice of America, New York
1949 October 30 - 1988 Broadcast weekly political commentaries, known as "Zapisnik," on Voice of America, under the name of Martin Cermak
1951-1953 Research Consultant on the Yale Human Resources Project, sponsored by the U.S. Army
1954-1980 Professor of political science, The City College of the City University of New York
1955-1956 Broadcast commentaries on international politics on Radio Free Europe
1981-1984 Member, Executive Committee, Center for European Studies, the City University of New York
1984 spring Visiting scholar, Institute of Governmental Studies, University of California, Berkeley
1988 March 1 Died, Kent, Connecticut
Scope and Content Note
The Ivo Duchacek papers were donated to the Hoover Institution Archives by Ivo Duchacek himself over a period of several years. The first installment, consisting of typewritten transcripts of his broadcasts on Voice of America and of cassettes of voice rehearsals of broadcasts, arrived in 1984. Duchacek's diaries covering the years 1939-1945 were accessioned in 1985, and additional radio broadcast transcripts were added to the collection in the years 1986 to 1988.
The bulk of the collection consists of Ivo Duchacek's speeches and writings and his radio broadcasts, mostly on Voice of America. For 39 years until his death, Duchacek delivered a weekly commentary over Voice of America, broadcast to Czechoslovakia under the pen name Martin Cermak. From 1949 to 1988, "The Sunday Notebook," as it was called, offered analyses of important world developments, evaluated American domestic and international policies, and in an informal and witty style interpreted life in the United States. At the same time, Duchacek's commentaries examined Czechoslovak history and conditions under Soviet domination, and with scathing criticism and sarcasm uncovered the true face of the Stalinist doctrine and practices (see his parody of the Slansky and Gottwald trials in the radio broadcasts file).
Of significant importance in the speeches and writings file are Duchacek's memoirs based on his political diaries kept throughout World War II, in which he exercised his intimite knowledge of the political scene and developments in Central Europe before and during the war (see, "In the Funnel of Two Tornadoes: The Nazi and Soviet Captures of the Heart of Europe. Political Diaries"). Equally important are his writings on the communist coup (see, "The Strategy of Communist Infiltration: Czechoslovakia, 1944-1948. The February Coup in Czechoslovakia") and the annexation of Ruthenia (see, "Soviet Annexation of Ruthenia: A Lesson in Soviet Browbeat Politics").
Also of great importance are documents in the government service file relating to the Soviet annexation of Ruthenia, and Duchacek's internal reports of discussions with foreign diplomats, agents, and journalists.
Indexing Terms
The following terms have been used to index the description of this collection in the repository's online public access catalog.
Subjects
Radio broadcasting--Czechoslovakia.; World War, 1939-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--Czechoslovakia.; Czechoslovakia.; Czechoslovakia--History--Coup d'état, 1948.; Ruthenia.; World War, 1939-1945--Diplomatic history.; Voice of America (Organization)
Genres and Forms of Material
Phonotapes.
Series Description
- Biographical File, 1939-1941. (Box 1)
  Identity papers, calling cards, list of names and addresses, arranged alphabetically by physical form
- Diaries, 1939-1945. (Box 1)
  Political diaries kept since March 1939 throughout the war until May 1945, arranged chronologically
- Correspondence, 1949-1952. (Box 1)
  Letters, notes, and telegrams, arranged alphabetically by name of correspondent
- Speeches and Writings, 1939-1988. (Box 2-3)
  Articles, papers, reports, speeches, and writings, arranged chronologically by title
- Radio Broadcasts, 1940-1988. (Box 4-23)
  Consists mostly of transcripts of broadcasts on the British Broadcasting Corporation, Radio Free Europe, Voice of America, and World Radio University, arranged alphabetically by broadcast station and therein chronologically
- Government Service, 1939-1948. (Box 24)
  Dispatches from Moscow to London relating to Soviet annexation of Ruthenia, internal reports of discussions in Paris and London with foreign diplomats, agents, journalists, and speeches, arranged alphabetically by physical form, and therein chronologically
- Subject File, 1939-1961. (Box 25)
  Articles, clippings, reports, speeches, writings, miscellany, clippings, and other printed matter, relating to various persons, organizations and countries, arranged alphabetically by subject
- Photographs, n.d. (Box 25)
  1 print depicting Ivo Duchacek and other individuals
- Phonotape Cassettes, 1977-1983. (Box Cassette cabinet)
  7 cassettes of voice rehearsals done at home before actual broadcasting
Container List
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1939-1941 (Box 1)
  - Identity papers issued by the Czechoslovak National Committee, Paris, 1940 (Folder 1: 1)
  - Calling cards (Folder 1: 2)
  - List of names and addresses (Folder 1: 3)
- DIARIES, 1939-1945.
  Political diaries kept since March 1939 throughout the war until May 1945. Typescript (mostly in Czech, some in French and English)
  - 1939 (Folder 1: 4)
  - 1940 (Folder 1: 5-6)
  - 1941 (Folder 1: 7-8)
  - 1942 (Folder 1: 9-10)
  - 1943 (Folder 1: 11-12)
  - 1944 (Folder 1: 13-14)
  - 1945 (Folder 1: 15)
- CORRESPONDENCE, 1949-1952
  - Dvornik, 1949 (Folder 1: 16)
  - Feierabend, Ladislav, 1940 (Folder 1: 17)
  - Firt, Julius, 1941 (Folder 1: 18)
  - Gottlieb, Hanus, 1941 (Folder 1: 19)
  - Heidrich, Arnost, 1949 (Folder 1: 20)
  - Lettrich, Jozef, 1949 (Folder 1: 21)
  - Mowrer, Edgar Ansel, 1949 (Folder 1: 22)
  - Nase Hlasy, 1958 (Folder 1: 23)
  - Pospisil, Leopold, 1951-1952 (Folder 1: 24)
  - Puhan, Alfred, 1950 (Folder 1: 25)
  - Rada Svobodneho Ceskoslovenska (Council of Free Czechoslovakia), 1949 (Folder 1: 26)
  - Speier, Hans, 1949 (Folder 1: 27)
  - United States. Department of State, 1949 (Folder 1: 28)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1939-1988 (Box 2)
  - "Americka pomoc Ceskoslovensku?" n.d. (Folder 2: 1)
    Typescript (in Czech)
  - "Analysis of the Communist Coup in Czechoslovakia," n.d. (Folder 2: 2)
    Typescript
  - "Dilemmas of the Doctrine of Liberation," n.d. (Folder 2: 3)
  - "In the Funnel of Two Tornadoes: The Nazi and Soviet Captures of the Heart of Europe. Political Diaries," n.d.
    Typescript of unfinished and unpublished memoirs
    - Part I - "The Fall of France: From Munich to Bordeaux" (Folder 2: 4-5)
    - Part II - "The British Fort - 1940-1941" (Folder 2: 6)
  - "The Lesson of Prague," n.d. (Folder 2: 7)
  - "The Purge ...... and After," n.d. (Folder 2: 8)
  - "The Present Situation in Czechoslovakia," report, International London Assembly, 1942. (Folder 2: 9)
  - "Cardinal Verdier and Mgr. Sramek," 1942 December 21. (Folder 2: 10)
    Typescript and printed copy (in English and Czech)
  - "Thirty Years of Czechoslovakia," 1948 October 28. (Folder 2: 11)
  - "Ruda armada zastrasila Evropu, New Yorkske Listy, 1949 August 23. (Folder 2: 12)
    Printed copy (in Czech)
  - "The Strategy of Communist Infiltration: Czechoslovakia, 1944-1948. The February Coup in Czechoslovakia," World Politics, 1950 July. (Folder 2: 13-14)
    Typescript and printed copy
  - "Liberation of Central Europe Through Neutralization," The New York Times, 1955 May 15 (date written). (Folder 2: 15)
  - "The Bonapartist Unity of Eastern Europe," The Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1955 October. (Box-folder 3: 1)
  - "The Classic Maneuver," 1957. (Folder 3: 2)
    Typescript. Includes correspondence with the editor of the New Leader
  - "A 'Loyal' Satellite: The Case of Czechoslovakia," The Annals of the American Academy of Political and Social Science, 1958 May. (Folder 3: 3)
    Printed copy
  - "East Central Europe: Soviet Internal Affair?" 1958 October. (Folder 3: 4)
    Typescript. Includes some correspondence
  - "Soviet Annexation of Ruthenia: A Lesson in Soviet Browbeat Politics," 1965 August?, See also RADIO BROADCASTS/Radio Free Europe and Voice of America, and GOVERNMENT SERVICE/Dispatches (Folder 3: 5)
    Typescript.
  - "National Constitutions: A Functional Approach," Comparative Politics, 1968 October. (Folder 3: 6)
  - "O zahranicne politickou orientaci CSR pred unorem," Svedectvi, 1973. (Folder 3: 7)
  - "External and Internal Challenges to the Federal Bargain," paper, Seminar on Urbanization in Federal Systems, Temple University, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1973 April 26. (Folder 3: 8)
  - "Antagonistic Cooperation: Territorial and Ethnic Communities," Publius: The Journal of Federalism, 1977 Fall. (Folder 3: 9)
  - "Federalist Responses to Ethnic Demands: An Overview," paper, the Second Paterson Conference on Federal Responses to Current Political Problems, 1978 January 29-February 2. (Folder 3: 10)
  - "Jak Ruda armada mapovala stredni Evropu: Tesinsko a Podkarpatsko, 1980 September. (Folder 3: 11)
    Typescript. Includes some correspondence and reviews by V. Precan and J. W. Brugel
  - "Consociations of Fatherlands: The Revival of Confederal Principles and Practices," conference paper, The Continuing Legacy of the Articles of Confederation, Temple University, Philadelphia, Pennsylvania, 1981 August 30-September 2. (Folder 3: 12)
  - "Perforated Sovereignties: Comparative Subnational Politics and their International Dimension," paper, 8th annual Political Science Conference, City University of New York, 1982 December 10. (Folder 3: 13)
  - "Transborder Linkages: Quebec, Canada, and the United States," paper, Research Group on Canadian-American Relations, Harvard University, 1982 December 11-12. (Folder 3: 14)
  - "Foreign Relations of Major Non-Capital Cities, New York and Montreal, Geneva and Strasbourg: Micro-Actors in International Politics," paper, annual meeting of the Study Group on Canadian-United States Relations, New York City, 1983 April 8-9. (Folder 3: 15)
  - "Transborder Regional Linkages in the Era of Interdependence," paper, Borderlands Studies Section, Albuquerque, New Mexico, 1983 April 27-30. (Folder 3: 16)
  - "Transborder Regionalism and Microdiplomacy: A Comparative Study," paper, Seminar on Canadian-United States Relations, Harvard University, 1983 December 6. (Folder 3: 17)
  - "Federalism: Constitutional and Majoritarian Mix in Systems of Institutionalized Territorial Segmentation," paper, annual meeting of the American Political Science Association, Chicago, Illinois, 1983 September 1-4. (Folder 3: 18)
  - "International Competence of Subnational Governments: Borderlands and Beyond," paper, conference on Comparative Borders, University of Texas, El Paso, 1984 March 20. (Folder 3: 19)
  - "Transborder Overlaps Between Three Federal Systems: From Gulf of Mexico to the Arctic Ocean," paper, Association of Borderlands Scholars, San Diego, 1984 April 25-28. (Folder 3: 20)
- RADIO BROADCASTS, 1940-1988. (Box 4)
  Consists mostly of typewritten transcripts. Includes some correspondence
  - British Broadcasting Corporation (BBC), Czechoslovak Programme (Folder 4: 1)
  - Radio Free Europe, Czechoslovak Desk
    - 1955 (Folder 4: 2-5)
    - 1963-1965. (Folder 4: 6-9)
      Includes Duchacek's writings on the annexation of Ruthenia
  - Voice of America, Czechoslovak Service (Box 5)
    - Correspondence, 1957-1975 (Folder 5: 1)
    - Transcripts
      - 1949. (Folder 5: 2-5)
      - 1950 (Folder 5: 6-8)
      - 1950 (Box-folder 6: 1-2)
      - 1951 (Folder 6: 3-8)
      - 1952. (Box-folder 7: 1-7)
        Includes parody of trials of Slansky and Gottwald by Duchacek
      - 1952 (Folder 8: 1)
      - 1953 (Folder 8: 2-7)
      - 1954 (Box-folder 9: 1-4)
      - 1955 (Folder 9: 5-7)
      - 1956 (Box-folder 10: 1-3)
      - 1957 (Folder 10: 4-6)
      - 1958 (Box-folder 11: 1-3)
      - 1959 (Folder 11: 4-6)
      - 1960 (Box-folder 12: 1-3)
      - 1961 (Folder 12: 4-6)
      - 1962 (Box-folder 13: 1-3)
      - 1963 (Folder 13: 4-6)
      - 1964 (Box-folder 14: 1-3)
      - 1965 (Folder 14: 4-6)
      - 1966 (Box-folder 15: 1-3)
      - 1967 (Folder 15: 4-6)
      - 1968 (Box-folder 16: 1-3)
      - 1969 (Folder 16: 4-6)
      - 1970 (Box-folder 17: 1-2)
      - 1971 (Folder 17: 3-4)
      - 1972 (Folder 17: 5-6)
      - 1973 (Box-folder 18: 1-2)
      - 1974 (Folder 18: 3-5)
      - 1975 (Box-folder 19: 1-3)
      - 1976 (Folder 19: 4-6)
      - 1977 (Box-folder 20: 1-3)
      - 1978 (Folder 20: 4-5)
      - 1979 (Box-folder 21: 1-2)
      - 1980 (Folder 21: 2-4)
      - 1981 (Folder 21: 5-6)
      - 1982 (Folder 21: 7-8)
      - 1983 (Box-folder 22: 1)
      - 1984 (Folder 22: 2-4)
      - 1985 (Folder 22: 5-6)
      - 1986 (Box-folder 23: 1-3)
      - 1987 (Folder 23: 4-5)
  - World Radio University (WRUL), Boston (Folder 23: 6)
- GOVERNMENT SERVICE, 1939-1948 (Box 24)
  - Dispatches from Moscow to London relating to the Soviet annexation of Ruthenia, 1944-1945., See also SPEECHES AND WRITINGS and RADIO BROADCASTS/Radio Free Europe and Voice of America (Folder 24: 1-2)
  - Reports (internal reports of discussions with foreign diplomats, agents, journalists, in Paris and London).
    Includes report on Slovak uprising and Benes's messages from London to the Protectorate
    - 1939-1941 (Folder 24: 3)
    - 1942 (Folder 24: 4)
    - 1943 (Folder 24: 5)
    - 1944 (Folder 24: 6-9)
    - 1945 (Folder 24: 10)
    - 1947 (Folder 24: 11)
    - 1948 (Folder 24: 12)
  - Speeches written for Hubert Ripka, 1943 (Folder 24: 13)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1939-1961. (Box 25)
  Articles, clippings, reports, speeches, writings, miscellany, clippings, and other printed matter
  - Czechoslovak-Polish Confederation (Proposed) (Folder 25: 1)
  - Czechoslovakia
    - Foreign relations
      - Germany. (Folder 25: 2)
        Includes "Nove reseni nemecke otazky v CSR" by Hubert Ripka
      - Soviet Union. (Folder 25: 3)
        Includes "Ceskoslovensko-sovetska smlouva" by Hubert Ripka
    - Government in Exile, Great Britain. (Folder 25: 4)
      Includes "The Czechoslovak Government-in-Exile During World War II" by Vojtech Mastny
    - Politics and government--1945-1992 (Folder 25: 5-6)
  - Czechoslovakia. Ministerstvo Zahranicnich Veci (Ministry of Foreign Affairs) (Folder 25: 7-8)
  - Czechoslovakia. Statni Rada (National Council) (Folder 25: 9)
  - Europe, Central. (Folder 25: 10-11)
    Includes printed copy of chapter of book by Stephen Denis Kertesz, The Fate of East Central Europe: Hopes and Failures of American Foreign Policy (written by Duchacek?)
  - Heydrich, Reinhard (Folder 25: 12)
  - Hurban, Vladimir Ladislav (Folder 25: 13)
  - Ripka, Hubert., See also GOVERNMENT SERVICE/Speeches (Folder 25: 14)
  - Slansky, Rudolf--Trials, litigation, etc.
    - Clippings (Folder 25: 15-16)
    - Transcripts of edited broadcasts of court proceedings, 1952 (Folder 25: 17-24)
  - Slovakia. (Folder 25: 25)
    Includes report to Statni Rada by General Sergej Ingr about the Slovak uprising
  - Slovakia. Slovenska narodni rada (Slovak National Council) (Folder 25: 26)
  - Sramek, Jan (Folder 25: 27)
  - World War, 1939-1945 (Folder 25: 28)
- PHOTOGRAPHS, n.d. (Folder 25: 29)
  One print depicting Ivo Duchacek and other individuals
- PHONOTAPE CASSETTES, 1977-1983. (Cassette-cabinet Cassette cabinet)